Guide to the Medical Manuscripts Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Medical manuscripts collection
1774-1971
MS 346
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
79.92
(100 containers)
This artificial collection is composed of correspondence, journals, account books, manuscripts, scrapbooks, and printed material relating to the study and practice of medicine, primarily in Connecticut and New York, primarily in the nineteenth century.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Medical Historical Library, 1980-1998.
Arrangement
Arranged by name of manuscript creator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This artificial collection is composed of correspondence, journals, account books, manuscripts, scrapbooks, and printed material relating to the study and practice of medicine, primarily in Connecticut and New York, primarily in the nineteenth century.
Medical education; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions; Medicine -- Practice -- Accounting; Medicine -- Study and teaching; World War, 1914-1918 -- Health aspects; Connecticut; New York (State); Physicians; Cushing, Harvey, 1869-1939; Tully family; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1900; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Hitchins, Clayton Stanley, 1934, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    TMS, notes of lectures in pathology and physiology probably given at Cornell University where Hitchins received his M.D. in 1938. 2v. ill. [Ithaca, N.Y.]
  - Conklin, William D., compiler, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    "The Jackson Health Resort, pioneer in its field as seen by those who knew it well, being an account of the institution's fiftieth anniversary with records of the seventieth and the one hundredth...and a supplement." Dansville, N.Y., 357 p. (electrostatic copy), ill. Original photographs and electrostatic copies of advertisements, menus and other memorabilia pasted in.
  - Tully, William (1785-1859), Circa 1808 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Ms notebook, "Sketches, historical and genealogical of the Tully family. Including an account of their first settlement in America, collected from manuscripts in possession of individuals as late as the year 1808." [ca. 1808?], l v. with two letters sewn in: ALS from Arthur Fenner, 1666/67 Oct 27 (with pencilled transcript), 2 p., ALS from Abigail Lee, [17__].
  - Heffron, John Lorenzo (1851-1924), 1872-, 1881-1882 winter (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Two ms notebooks: "A review of Portus' intellectual science, commenced December 2, 1872," and medical case notes taken in Vienna and Heidelberg, winter 1881-1882. 2 v.
  - Allen, Edgar (1892-1943), 1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, photographs, blue prints and memoranda related to an exhibition titled "Human Eggs and Ovarian Hormones" at the Century of Progress Exposition in Chicago, 1933, to which Allen was a contributor. Twenty-two photostats reproduce the display. 35 items.
  - Horrax, Gilbert (1887-1957), 1917 April 29 - 1919 November 10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Letters (typed copies) to his family in Colebrook, Conn., while Horrax was serving as a doctor in an army base hospital in France under Dr. Harvey Cushing. 1 v.
  - Heffren, John, Jr., 1809 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Two ms notebooks: (1) Notes and extracts from courses in chemical and anatomical sciences, delivered at Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H., during 1809 by Dr. Nathan Smith. (2) Receipts, materia medica and miscellaneous medical notes, 2 v.
  - Austin, Ella H. (McLean), 1917 August - 1920 March (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Documents relating to her service in the American Red Cross, as a member of the French and Serbian Commissions during World War I, August 1917 - March 1920. 4 items.
  - Fowler Phrenological Institute, London, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 8a)
    Twelve lessons on phrenology, for the year of 1904, 12 pts. (mimeographed).
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings with anecdotes, medical remedies and accounts of medical curiosities. 1 v., 1871-1889 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lockwood, Howard De Forest (d.1958), Circa 1901 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Six ms notebooks related to his medical studies. These include two notebooks with his notes for lectures on chemistry and physiology at Yale College (1901), a notebook describing the characteristic course of common diseases, and three sketch books with colored drawings of abnormal cells.
  - Arnold, Harold Sears (1877-1951), 1947, 1952 March (Box 6, Folder 11)
    TMS, "Recollections of fifty years. An autobiography." New Haven, Conn., 1947 3 v. With mounted photographs laid in. Also included is a ms tribute by Daphne S. Townsend, her correspondence relating to the autobiography (1953-1954) and a printed obituary from the Connecticut State Medical Journal.
  - Lane, Irvin J., 1880-1883 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    Five ms notebooks containing notes on courses in pharmacology, mental diseases, obstetrics, physical diagnosis and physiology as taught at the Homeopathic Medical College in New York City.
  - Beckwith, Frank Edwin, 1868-1871 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Six ms notebooks, of which one is a volume of notes on lectures and clinics at Bellevue Medical College (1868-1869), three record medical lectures at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York City (ca.1870-1871) and two contain brief miscellaneous notes, largely on remedies (1868-1871).
  - Hubbard, Thomas (1776-1838), 1829-1830
    Transferred to YRG-47-J, 1982 May 19.
    Ms notebooks with lectures on surgery delivered at Yale College. 5 v., numbered 3, 4, 5, 6, 8. A number of the volumes contain notes on the subsequent dates that the lectures were delivered, the latest being 1837.
    Contents: Box 11, v.3, 4; Box 12, v.5, 6, 8.
  - Lane, John Edward (1872-1933), 1915-1933 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    Papers, 1915-1933
    2.5 inches
    Physician. Correspondence, writings and printed matter documenting his career as a specialist in dermatology and syphilogy. Included also is a list of his publication and a list prepared by him of the medical books in the 1742 library of Yale College.
- Additional materials, 1777-1945; Accession 1982-M-014
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of materials transferred from the Medical Historical Library in 1982. It is composed almost entirely of bound volumes such as account books and notebooks from the practices of several doctors. The materials date from 1777 through 1945. Most of the records come from New England, though there are a few items from Civil War Virginia and from New York.
  - Bronson, A. [daybook], 1797-1805 (Box 1)
  - Woodward, ____
    - Daybook, 1829-1833 (Box 1A)
    - Ledger, 1833-1859 (Box 1B–1C)
  - Barr, Lockwood [biography of Dr. Joseph Strong, 2 copies], 1940 (Box 2)
  - Calhoun, S. H. [ledger from Washington, CT], 1831-1840 (Box 2A)
  - Calkins, D. [case register from Fisher's Island, NY], 1850-1854 (Box 2B)
  - Canfield, Joel
    - Daybook, 1824-1828 (Box 2C)
    - Daybook, 1828-1831 (Box 2D)
    - Daybook, 1831-1835 (Box 3)
  - Unidentified
    - Daybook, 1850-1855 (Box 3A)
    - Daybook, 1844-1850 (Box 3B)
    - Daybook, 1837-1839 (Box 3C)
    - Ledger, 1834-1836 (Box 3D)
    - Daybook, 1856-1874 (Box 3E)
  - Canfield, Joel [daybook], 1858-1871 (Box 3F)
  - Castiglioni, ____ [notes on forensic medicine by a student at New York University], 1944-1945 (Box 4)
  - Castle, Jeremiah [Bethany, CT]
    - Daybook, 1819-1822 (Box 4A)
    - Ledger, 1822-1846 (Box 4B)
  - Haven, Samuel Rush [Virginia]
    - Notebook, 1862 (Box 32, Folder 20)
    - Letterbook as brigade surgeon, 1861-1862 (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - Daggett, D. L. [New Haven, CT]
    - Register of patients with services rendered, 1872-1884 (Box 4C)
    - Daybook, 1854-1865, 1849-1854 (Box 29, Folder 23-24)
    - Ledger, 1828-1846 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Daybook, 1866-1896 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Check counterfoil, 1868-1874 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Register of patients with services rendered, 1863-1872 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Check counterfoil, 1882-1890 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Register of receipts, 1883-1895, 1865-1881 (Box 5, Folder 30-31)
    - Case register, 1841-1892 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Downs, Myron B. [Roxbury, CT]
    - Daybooks
      - 1833-1846 (Box 6)
      - 1837-1839 (Box 6A)
      - 1834-1836 (Box 6B)
      - 1839-1841 (Box 6C)
      - 1841-1844 (Box 6D)
      - 1844-1846 (Box 6E)
      - 1846-1848 (Box 6F)
      - 1849-1852 (Box 6G)
      - 1853 February-1858 April (Box 7)
      - 1858 April-1961 September (Box 7A)
      - 1861 September-1865 March (Box 7B)
      - 1865 March 2-1869 March 3 (Box 7C)
      - 1869 March 8-1874 March 8 (Box 7D)
      - 1874 May-1880 August (Box 7E)
      - 1880 November 19-1886 June 9 (Box 7F)
    - Account book, 1840-1870 (Box 7G)
    - Ledger
      - 1833-1851 (Box 8)
      - 1849-1882 (Box 8A)
    - Prescriptions, 1848-1869 (Box 8B)
    - Charges for letters and papers
      - 1840-1845 (Box 8C)
      - 1847-1848 (Box 8D)
    - Charges for magazines and papers, 1847-1849 (Box 8E)
  - Fowler, Remus M. [Washington, CT]
    - Ledger, 1826-1840 (Box 9)
    - Daybook
      - 1835 January 1-1838 February 9 (Box 9A)
      - 1838 February 10-1840 April 15 (Box 9B)
    - Account book, 1841-1863 (Box 9C)
  - Allen, Henry [volume containing transcription of deeds from Norwich, CT], 1828-1847 (Box 9D)
  - Downs, Myron B.
    - Register of letters sent and account of mail received, 1833-1849 (Box 10)
    - Account of mail sent, 1841-1842 (Box 10)
  - New Haven Hospital Eye Clinic [admitting book], 1896-1902 (Box 10A)
  - Utley, Vine
    - "Observations on the Influenza in the Year 1807" [paper delivered before the Medical Society in New London, CT], 1808 (Box 30, Folder 63)
    - Medical register [record of cases attended in the towns of Lyme, Waterford, and Montville, indexed by ailment, vol. 1, 3, 4, 7, 8], 1802-1835 (Box 30, Folder 63A-63E)
  - Utley, Leander [notes from lectures delivered by Nathan Smith on theory and practice of physic, Yale College], 1816 (Box 30, Folder 64)
  - Jewett and Townsend [account book of professional services rendered], 1862 (Box 31, Folder 65)
  - Linsly, ____ [ledger] (with DK), 1816-1824 (Box 11)
  - Osgood, Erastus
    - Daybook
      - 1837-1841 (Box 12)
      - 1841-1847 (Box 12A)
      - 1847-1853 (Box 12B)
  - Palmer, G. E. [ledger], 1831-1860 (Box 12C)
  - Osgood, Erastus
    - Medical prescripta, 1831 (Box 12D)
    - Notes on individual cases, 1790s-1800s (Box 12E)
    - Account book, 1804-1823 (Box 12F)
    - Ledger, 1832-1850 (Box 13)
    - Daybook
      - 1811-1813 (Box 13A)
      - 1815-1819 (Box 13B)
    - Daybook
      - 1819-1822 (Box 14)
      - 1822-1825 (Box 14A)
      - 1832-1837 (Box 14B)
  - Palmer, G. E. [notes on lectures by Dr. Francis and Dr. Hosack at the N.Y. Hospital], 1825 (Box 14C)
  - Pierson, William Seward [Windsor, CT]
    - Ledger, 1812-1818 (Box 15)
    - Daybook
      - 1814 January 1-1815 January 27 (Box 15A)
      - 1815 January 27-1816 April 30 (Box 15B)
      - 1816 May 1-1817 February (Box 15C)
      - 1817 March 1-1818 November 17 (Box 15D)
    - Ledger
      - 1818-1829 (Box 16)
      - 1823-1832 (Box 16A)
    - Daybook, 1831-1835 (Box 17, Folder 88-90)
    - Daybook, 1833-1838 (Box 18, Folder 91-94)
    - Daybook, 1840-1848 (Box 19, Folder 95-97)
    - Daybook, 1848-1860, 1838-1840 (Box 20, Folder 98-101)
    - Daybook, 1818-1820, 1826-1829, 1820-1822 (Box 21, Folder 102-104)
    - Ledger, 1831-1845 (Box 22, Folder 105-106)
    - Ledger, 1843-1861 (Box 23, Folder 107)
  - Root, Josiah [ledger from Southington, CT], 1790-1795 (Box 23, Folder 108)
  - Holmes, Chris. [ledger], 1789-1814 (Box 24, Folder 109)
  - Hoxie, Thomas Burton
    - Student notebook of patients seen, 1816-1817 (Box 24, Folder 110)
    - Ledger, 1829-1835 (Box 24, Folder 111)
  - Hutchinson, Ira [ledger from Haddam, CT], 1825-1830 (Box 25)
  - Poor, Joshua [ledger from Stratford, CT], 1777-1795 (Box 25A)
  - Stanton, D. [medicinal and miscellaneous recipes], 1869-1917 (Box 25B)
  - Story, Dyer [Windsor, VT]
    - Daybook, 1836-1843, 1860-1868 (Box 26, Folder 115-116)
  - Plumbs, Ovid [daybook], 1812-1814 (Box 26, Folder 117)
  - Turner, Sylvester Wooster [daybook from Chester, CT], 1853-1859 (Box 27, Folder 118)
  - Ward, ____ [daybook], 1861-1867 (Box 27, Folder 119)
  - Wilcox, L. [daybook from Hartford, CT], 1857 (Box 27, Folder 120)
  - Rice, Foster Wild [scrapbook, including photographs, clippings, and correspondence, from his service in France during World War I and material related to his veteran's status], 1917-1918, 1924-1939 (Box 28, Folder 121)
- Additional materials, 1774-1923; Accession 1984-M-001
  - Physicians' records [some physicians' prescription books are listed under pharmacology files]
    - Buzzell, J. D. [account book], 1819-1830 (Box 1)
    - Everitt, Josiah [account book], 1774-1794 (Box 1)
    - Woodward, Samuel Bayard [account book], 1829-1832 (Box 1)
    - Sparrow, Lewis G.
      - Account book [Baltimore], 1854-1869 (Box 1)
      - Diary [from Dickinson College, Carlisle, PA], 1849-1850 (Box 1)
    - Downs, Myron
      - Account book, Circa 1833 (Box 2)
      - Lecture notes [includes "Diseases of Children," by Eli Ives, M.D.], Circa 1829 (Box 2)
    - Knight, Jonathan
      - Visiting list
        - 1853 1853 (Box 2)
        - 1856 1856 (Box 2)
        - 1858 1858 (Box 2)
        - 1859 1859 (Box 2)
        - 1861 1861 (Box 2)
  - Pharmacology files
    - Spalding, W. A. [prescription book], undated (Box 3)
    - Shand, [James?] [prescription and account book], 1841 (Box 3)
    - Cambell, Robert [prescription material], undated (Box 3)
    - Woodward, Samuel Bayard [and H.?]
      - Account book, 1819-1820 (Box 4)
      - Account book, 1821-1822
        See also: box 5
    - Anonymous [prescription book, mid-seventeenth century England] (Box 4)
    - Anonymous [prescription book], undated (Box 4)
    - Edwards, Mrs. Lincoln [prescription book; includes Botany, Farmer's Materia Medica, Sulphur Rock, Arkansas], 1847-1848 (Box 4)
    - Kilbourn, J. A. [prescription book], Circa 1900-1910 (Box 4)
    - Root, J. [prescription book], 1802-1806 (Box 4)
    - Spalding, W. A. [prescription book], undated (Box 4)
    - Woodward, Samuel Bayard [account book], 1821-1822 (Box 5)
  - Lecture notes
    - Archibald, Ronald [anatomy], 1923 (Box 6)
    - Woodbury, Peter L.
      - Dr. Howe's notes on Benjamin Rush's lectures; copied by Woodbury, 1811-1812 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous notes on physiology, lead, etc., 1813 (Box 6)
      - Colonel Rufus Graves's lectures on chemistry, Hanover, N.H., 1813 (Box 6)
      - Essays on lead and cancer; miscellaneous course materials, 1813-1814 (Box 6)
    - Stanton, George D. [Journal of Didactic and Clinical Lectures] from Bellevue Hospital and Medical; College, 1863-1864 (Box 6)
    - Hosack, David [lectures on the theory and practice of physics and institutes of medicine] from College of Physicians and Surgeons of the state of New York, 1821-1822 (Box 6)
    - Anonymous [notes on astrology in medical practice], undated (Box 6)
- Additional materials, 1931-1962; Accession 1999-M-070
  Transfer date from Medical Historical Library unknown. Accessioned in 1998 as part of processing room backlog.
  - Eisenhardt, Louise
    - Correspondence relating to published works by Harvey Williams Cushing, primarily The Meningiomas, of which Eisenhardt was a co-author, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Light, Richard Upjohn
    - Correspondence, research notes, and writings, dating from the time when Light served as a fellow in the Laboratory of Surgical Research at the Harvard University Medical School and worked with Harvey Williams Cushing, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - New York (N.Y.) Dept. of Hospitals
    - Prospectus for internship applicants containing information on and photographs of City Hospital, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)